<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../Common/Overview.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<VSSDKSample>
  <ImagePath>../../../../Common</ImagePath>
  <Status>
    <Accessibility>true</Accessibility>
    <ArchitectureDiagram>false</ArchitectureDiagram>
    <Comments>true</Comments>
    <Documentation>true</Documentation>
    <ErrorHandling>true</ErrorHandling>
    <FollowSDKCodingStandards>true</FollowSDKCodingStandards>
    <Localizable>true</Localizable>
    <Overview>true</Overview>
    <ScenarioTests>true</ScenarioTests>
    <Supported>true</Supported>
    <UnitTests>true</UnitTests>
    <Style>Example</Style>
  </Status>
  <Overview>
    <ShortName>C# Example.ExtendedProvider</ShortName>
    <LongName>C# Extended DDEX Provider Sample</LongName>
    <Phrase>Demonstrates how to implement a scenario-complete DDEX provider.</Phrase>
  </Overview>
  <Introduction>
    <Summary>
      This sample demonstrates how to implement a DDEX provider based on the
      .NET Framework Data Provider for SQL Server that supports all the common
      data design time scenarios.
    </Summary>
    <Goal>Supplying all features of the basic DDEX provider sample</Goal>
    <Goal>Embedding the XML support files as assembly resources</Goal>
    <Goal>Customizing the data object selector service</Goal>
    <Goal>Customizing the data object identifier resolver service</Goal>
    <Goal>Customizing the data source information service</Goal>
    <Goal>Enabling localization of many exposed strings</Goal>
    <Goal>Supporting all the common data design time scenarios</Goal>
  </Introduction>
  <SampleInfo>
    <State>New</State>
    <Type>Example</Type>
    <Complexity>1</Complexity>
    <Screenshot />
    <Area>Data</Area>
    <Language>C#</Language>
    <Folder>VisualStudioIntegration\Samples\Data\CSharp\Example.ExtendedProvider\</Folder>
    <SampleSolution>ExtendedProvider.sln</SampleSolution>
    <FolderUnitTest>VisualStudioIntegration\Samples\Data\CSharp\Example.ExtendedProvider\UnitTests</FolderUnitTest>
    <UnitTestStartup>ExtendedProvider.UnitTests.csproj</UnitTestStartup>
    <Doc />
    <Keywords>
      <Keyword>Data</Keyword>
      <Keyword>DDEX</Keyword>
      <Keyword>Provider</Keyword>
    </Keywords>
  </SampleInfo>
  <GettingStarted>
    <Paragraph>
      This sample focuses on fixing the issues surrounding the data design time
      scenarios that were in the basic DDEX provider sample.  This is done by
      providing an assembly containing code that customizes key parts of the
      provider.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      The main addition in this sample is a custom data object selector to
      supplement or in some cases replace the schema information returned by
      the .NET Framework Data Provider for SQL Server.  This includes providing
      information such as the server instance name, the default schema, as well
      as collections like indexes and index columns (which include primary
      and unique keys), foreign keys and foreign key columns, stored procedures
      and stored procedure parameters and columns, and user-defined functions
      and user-defined function parameters and columns.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      A further addition is a custom object identifier resolver, which
      correctly expands an identifier based on the active connection.  For
      example, if the identifier "Customers" is supplied, the active connection
      can expand this to "Northwind.dbo.Customers" based on the current active
      database and default schema in that database.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      Other enhancements include a customized data source information class
      to return properties that require computing and the localization of
      some strings.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      Due to the extensions added in this sample, this provider will only
      connect to instances of Microsoft SQL Server 2005 or later.  Also note
      that table-valued functions with parameters are not supported in some
      data design scenarios due to a lack of extensibility in this area.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      Since there is already a DDEX provider based on the .NET Framework Data
      Provider for SQL Server that ships with Visual Studio, installing another
      such provider has potential for ambiguity, as many data design scenarios
      refer to the ADO.NET provider invariant name only and from this there is
      a one-to-many mapping to DDEX providers.  To ensure that this sample DDEX
      provider is being used for the various data design scenarios, make sure
      the last selected data source and provider combination in the data
      connection dialog uses this sample DDEX provider.  Visual Studio
      incorporates a heuristic for determining the correct DDEX provider to use
      given an ADO.NET invariant name that is based on the last provider
      selection made for each registered DDEX data source.
    </Paragraph>
  </GettingStarted>
  <BuildingTheSample>
    <Step>
      Open the <bold>ExtendedProvider.sln</bold> solution.
    </Step>
    <Step>
      Press F5 to build the sample and register it in the experimental hive,
      then launch Visual Studio from the experimental hive.
    </Step>
    <Step>
      Alternatively, run the <bold>Install.cmd /ranu</bold> script from a
      command line, passing in a Visual Studio registry root (optional) and
      location of the built assembly binary (required). The Visual Studio
      registry root defaults to the SDK experimental hive.  Exclude the
      <bold>/ranu</bold> argument when installing to a non-experimental Visual
      Studio registry hive.
    </Step>
  </BuildingTheSample>
  <RunningTheSample>
    <SampleTask>
      <Description>
        To add a data connection...
      </Description>
      <Step>
        On the <bold>View</bold> menu, click <bold>Server Explorer</bold>.
      </Step>
      <Step>
        In the <bold>Server Explorer</bold> window, right click the <bold>Data
        Connections</bold> node and choose <bold>Add Connection...</bold>.
      </Step>
      <Step>
        If the <bold>Add Connection</bold> dialog shows, click the <bold>
        Change...</bold> button to show the <bold>Change Data Source</bold>
        dialog.
      </Step>
      <Step>
        Pick the <bold>Microsoft SQL Server</bold> data source and drop down
        the <bold>Data Provider</bold> combo box, then choose this sample's
        data provider (marked as "Extended Sample").
      </Step>
      <Step>
        Click <bold>OK</bold> to move to the <bold>Add Connection</bold>
        dialog.
      </Step>
      <Step>
        In the property grid, enter information to connect to an instance of
        Microsoft SQL Server.  For the SQL Express instance installed by
        default with Visual Studio, enter ".\SQLEXPRESS" as the <bold>Data
        Source</bold> value.
      </Step>
      <Step>
        Click <bold>OK</bold> to create a connection in the Server Explorer.
      </Step>
    </SampleTask>
    <SampleTask>
      <Description>
        To enumerate data objects...
      </Description>
      <Step>
        Follow the steps for adding a data connection with this provider.
      </Step>
      <Step>
        Expand the resulting data connection.
      </Step>
      <Step>
        Expand the various nodes to see data objects.
      </Step>
    </SampleTask>
    <SampleTask>
      <Description>
        To initiate an end-to-end data design time scenario
      </Description>
      <Step>
        Create a new VB or C# project.
      </Step>
      <Step>
        On the <bold>Data</bold> menu, click <bold>Show Data Sources</bold>.
      </Step>
      <Step>
        In the <bold>Data Sources</bold> window, click <bold>Add New Data
        Source...</bold>.
      </Step>
      <Step>
        Follow the steps in the Data Source Configuration Wizard.
      </Step>
    </SampleTask>
  </RunningTheSample>
  <AdditionalResources>
    <Resource>
      <Title>Visual Studio SDK Website</Title>
      <URL>http://msdn.microsoft.com/vstudio/extend</URL>
    </Resource>
  </AdditionalResources>
  <UnitTests>
    <Test>
      SqlObjectIdentifierResolverTests.ExpandIdentifierTest.  Ensure an
      identifier "Customers" is properly expanded to "Northwind", "dbo",
      "Customers" given appropriate mocks that return a hard coded default
      catalog and schema.
    </Test>
    <Test>
      SqlObjectSelectorTests.SelectObjectsTest.  Ensure all the different
      enumerations execute successfully and in some cases, check the actual
      returned result set.
    </Test>
    <Test>
      SqlSourceInformationTests.ItemIndexerTest.  Ensure retrieval of the
      default schema executes successfully and returns the correct value.
    </Test>
  </UnitTests>
  <FunctionalTests>
    <Test>
      See the DDEX SDK documentation for information about functional tests.
    </Test>
  </FunctionalTests>
  <ProjectFiles>
    <File>
      <Name>ExtendedProvider.reg</Name>
      <Description>
        This file contains the registry entries that register this provider.
      </Description>
    </File>
    <File>
      <Name>SqlObjectIdentifierResolver.cs</Name>
      <Description>
        This file contains the custom implementation of the data object
        identifier resolver connection service.
      </Description>
    </File>
    <File>
      <Name>SqlObjectSelector.cs</Name>
      <Description>
        This file contains the custom implementation of the data object
        selector connection service.
      </Description>
    </File>
    <File>
      <Name>SqlObjectSupport.xml</Name>
      <Description>
        This file defines the structure of the data source as a set of objects.
      </Description>
    </File>
    <File>
      <Name>SqlObjectTypes.cs</Name>
      <Description>
        This file contains static strings identifying the different types of
        objects defined in the data object support XML file, for programmatic
        purposes.
      </Description>
    </File>
    <File>
      <Name>SqlSourceInformation.cs</Name>
      <Description>
        This file contains the custom implementation of the data source
        information connection service.
      </Description>
    </File>
    <File>
      <Name>SqlViewSupport.xml</Name>
      <Description>
        This file defines the presentation of the data source objects in a
        hierarchical form.
      </Description>
    </File>
  </ProjectFiles>
  <History>
    <Change>
      <Date>2007-07-08</Date>
      <Description>
        Created this sample for the Visual Studio 2008 SDK.
      </Description>
    </Change>
  </History>
</VSSDKSample>